Guide to the Ernst Jäckh Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Ernst Jäckh Papers,
1900-1961
Jäckh, Ernst.
13 linear ft. (ca. 2,000 items in 6 boxes, 16 file boxes, 12 scrapbooks).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078934
Biographical Note
Author and academic (1875-1959), was born in Urach, Germany. He promoted the German-Turkish Alliance (1908-1914), founded the German Turkish Association (1912), and became professor of Turkish history at the University of Berlin (1914). Jäckh was a member of the diplomatic service during World War I, and, with Friedrich Naumann, an organizer of the liberal movement in Germany (1902-1912). He helped found the German League of Nations and the Hochschule für Politik. Jäckh emigrated to Britain in the 1930s and held the position of international director of the New Commonwealth Institute until 1940 when he became Professor of Public Law and Government at Columbia University, specializing in the politics of Germany, the Balkans, and the Middle East. His published books include: Albanian War; Der Austeigende Halbmonde; Background of the Middle East; Deutschland im Orient; and Des Goldenen Pflug.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, memorabilia, photographs, and printed materials. The correspondence consists of letters relating to the publication and review of Jäckh's books, articles, and book reviews and typescript copies of letters by Hans Jäckh. There are manuscripts for his articles, lectures and speeches as well as clipping files of book reviews and articles by and about Jäckh in the European and North American press. The bulk of the collection is written and printed in German and deals with the Balkans and the Near East before 1920, including the Balkan War of 1912-1914, and the Turkish Revolution. Of particular interest are manuscripts and articles describing his land travels between 1903 and 1913 with the German fleet and on hot air balloons. Other topics covered include the Hocjschule für Politik, German labor unions, German-European relations, European attitudes towards the United States, and his literary works. There are also some manuscripts dealing with the Balkans and the Near East during World War II. An extensive file of photographs depicts, Albania, Asia Minor, Baghdad, the Balkans, Constantinople, Genoa, the German naval fleet, the Hochschule für Politik, hot air balloons, Italy, the Mediterranean, Turkey, the Turkish Revolution, the United States, Versailles, and Weimar. There are books from Jäckh's library, some with marginal notes, some signed and inscribed to him as well as copies of his own works.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series I: Correspondence, Manuscripts Memorabilia
Series II: Photographs and Printed Materials
Series III: Photographs
Series IV: Manuscripts and Printed Materials
Series V: Scrapbooks
Series VI: Books from the Library of Ernst Jäckh
Subjects
Columbia University--Faculty.; Hochschule für Politik München.; Jäckh, Hans.; Baghdad (Iraq)--Photographs.; Balkan Peninsula.; Bulgaria--Politics and government.; Genoa (Italy)--Photographs.; Germany--Armed Forces.; Germany--Politics and government.; Istanbul (Turkey)--Photographs.; Mediterranean Sea--Photographs.; Middle East--Politics and government.; Turkey--Foreign relations--Germany.; Turkey--History--Revolution, 1909.; United States--Foreign public opinion.; Versailles (France)--Photographs.; Weimar (Thuringia, Germany)--Photographs.; Hot air balloons.; Law--Study and teaching.; Political science--Study and teaching.; Political science--Research.; Labor unions--Germany.; Announcements.; Articles.; Lectures.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Proofs.; Reviews.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches.; Authors.; College teachers.; Journalists.; Political scientists.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1959 M-59 Anshen, Ruth Nanda Gift
- Series I: Correspondence, Manuscripts Memorabilia
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence
    - Letters, telegrams and postcards re: publication and reviews of his books, 1908-1913 (Box 1)
    - Jäckh, Hans To Veronica Jäckh, 1915-1918, ( t.ms. transcripts) (Box 1)
    - Jäckh, Hans To his parents, 1917-1918, ( t.ms. transcripts) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1953-1961 (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.2: Manuscript
    - Des Goldenen Pflug - Outline for book (Box 1)
    - "Turkey" (in Encyclopedia Americana), 1945, ( Proof with corrections) (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.3: Memorabilia
    - Memorial Service at Columbia, 1959 (Box 1)
- Series II: Photographs and Printed Materials
  - Subseries II.1: Photographs
    - Turkey, (2 folders, 3 unfoldered photos on boards) (Box 2)
  - Subseries II.2: Printed Materials
    - Book Reviews of Jäckh's Background of the Middle East by Jäckh (Box 2)
    - Jäckh, Ernst Articles in Der Schabenspiegel, Sept. 15, 1900-May 11, 1901 (Box 2)
    - Jäckh, Ernst Biographical Sketches of German Political Figures (Box 2)
    - Jäckh, Ernst Deutschen Werkbundes (Box 2)
    - Jäckh, Ernst Turkey (Box 2)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Türkische Studierenreisen in Deutschland, 1911, ( photographs) (Box 3)
  - Türkische Revolution: Adana, Dard anellen, Tripolis, ( photographs) (Box 4)
  - Balkan; Mittelmeer; Italien (Box 4)
  - Genoa (Box 5)
  - Kaiserreise; Konstantin und Grundsteinlegung (Box 5)
  - Luftsschiffart und Flotte [Hot air balloons and German naval fleet] (Box 6)
  - Amerika; Hochschule für Politik (Box 6)
  - Konstantinopel; Kleinasien; Bagdad (Box 7)
  - Albanien (Box 7)
  - Türken und Türkinnen (Box 8)
  - Versailles; Weimar (Box 8)
- Series IV: Manuscripts and Printed Materials
  - Amerika: Manuscripts re European attitude towards America (Box 9)
  - Literarische Arbeiten (Schwaben; Vortrüge; Heilbronn): Manuscripts and Printed Articles (Box 9)
  - Vorträge und Vorlesungen (Balkans & Near East during World War II): Manuscripts (Box 10)
  - Vorträge und Vorlesungen: Manuscripts and Printed Articles, 1920-1940 (Box 10)
- Series V: Scrapbooks
  - #19: Ausländische Kritiken, 1926-1932. Printed articles and typescripts in foreign publications about Jäckh and his activities, 1926; printed articles by Jäckh, 1926-32. (Box 11)
  - #20: Bücher Besprechungen, 1911-1913: Anno uncements and reviews for Der Austeigende Halbmonde, Deutschland im Orient & Albanian War. (Box 11)
  - #21: Kritiken: Kiderlen Wächter, 1924 [Book reviews] (Box 12)
  - #22: Kritiken über Jäckh, 1902-1908 [Articles about Jäckh in German publications, including some typescripts] (Box 12)
  - #23: Amerika und Wir, 1929-1930 [Book reviews in German publications] (Box 13)
  - #24: Canadasche und Amerikanen Kritiken, 1926-1931 [Articles about Jäckh in Canadian, U.S, and South American publications. Includes several letters to Jäckh] (Box 13)
  - #25: Politische Artikel: Türkei, 1912-1914 [Articles by Jäckh: Balkankrieg, 1912-14; Weltkrieg, 1914] (Box 14)
  - #26: Politische Artikel: Türkei,: Türkei,1908-1914 [JungTürkische Revolution] (Box 14)
  - # 27: Politische Artikel: Länder, E-S,1914-1915 [Articles by Jäckh on German-European relations] (Box 15)
  - #28: Politische Artikel: General and Bulgaria, 1913- 1924 [Articles by Jäckh] (Box 15)
  - #29: Deutsche Besprechungen, 1931-1933 [Announcements and articles about Jäckh chiefly relating to the Hochschule für Politik, Werkersbundes, reviews or commentary on his writings, and a number of his own manuscripts] (Box 16)
  - #30: Reise Besprechungen, 1903-1913 [Articles and t.ms. by Jäckh describing his travels on land, with the German fleet, and on hot air balloons] (Box 16)
- Series VI: Books from the Library of Ernst Jäckh
  - Some books contain Jäckh's marginal notes and others are signed and inscribed to him. (Box 17-20)